Chandler, Alfred D., 1918-2007. Papers, 1941-2004: A Finding Aid
Alfred D. Chandler papers, 1940-2007
- Series IX. Biographical Materials, 1947-2007
  - Subseries B. Awards, certificates and degrees, 1947-2003
    This subseries consists of various awards, certificates and degrees that Alfred Chandler acquired over his nearly 60 years as a business historian. Some of the materials also include a small amount of correspondence and other related records. Of particular interest is Chandler’s Distinguished Service Award from Harvard University and related materials, 1995.
    - Award, Business Library Review (plaque), undated (Box 248, f. 1)
    - Membership certificate, Association for the Management of Organization Design, undated (Box 232, f. 11)
    - Scholarly Contributions to Management Award, Academy of Management, undated., (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 5)
    - Master of Arts, Harvard University, 20 October 1947, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 2)
    - Master of Arts, University of North Carolina, 18 December 1951 (Map case)
    - The Newcomen Award in Business History, 1st Prize, Newcomen Society, 5 November 1959 (Box 232, f. 12)
    - The Thomas Newcomen $1000 Award in Business History, Newcomen Society, 8 August 1964 (Box 232, f. 13)
    - Award, Optimists International, 11 May 1966 (Box 232, f. 14)
    - Membership certificate, National Advisory Council on Education Professions Development (signed by President Nixon), 29 April 1970, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 2)
    - Membership certificate (Fellow), American Academy of the Arts and Sciences, 12 May 1971, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 3)
    - Honorary Doctorate, Catholic University of Leuven (Belgium), 2 Februrary1976 (Box OS 5)
    - Catholic University of Leuven letter, 1976 (Box 232, f. 15)
    - Catholic University of Leuven medal, 1976 (Box 247, item 2)
    - Catholic University of Leuven honorary hat, 1976, (oversized) (Box OS 1)
    - Catholic University of Leuven ashtray, 1976 (Box 247, item 11)
    - Membership certificate, American Antiquarian Society, 19 April 1978, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 4)
    - Honorary Doctorate, Antwerp University, 1979, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 6)
    - The Thomas Newcomen $1000 Award in Business History, Newcomen Society, March 1980 (Box 232, f. 16)
    - Honorary Degree, Italian Acadamy of Business Economy, 21 November 1980, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 4)
    - Walker-Ames Professor, University of Washington, Spring Quarter 1981 (Box 249, f. 1)
    - Doctor of Humane Letters, Babson College, 22 May 1982 (Box 249, f. 2)
    - Membership certificate, American Philosophical Society, 20 April 1984, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 5)
    - Doctor of Humane Letters, Ohio State University (honoris causa), 20 March 1987 (Box 249, f. 3)
    - Doctor of Humane Letters (plaque), Ohio State University (honoris causa), 20 March 1987 (Box 248, f. 2)
    - Doctor of Laws (honoris causa), York University (Canada), 17 June 1988 (Box 249, f. 4)
    - Doctor of Laws (honoris causa), York University (Canada), 17 June 1988, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 6)
    - Fellow, Academy of Management, 14 August 1990, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 7)
    - Leo Melamed Prize, University of Chicago Graduate School of Business, 13 April 1992 (Box 249, f. 5)
    - Doctor of Laws (Honorary), New England College, 10 May, 1992 (Map case)
    - Distinguished Service Award, Harvard University, 3 June 1995, (oversized) (Box OS 1)
    - Distinguished Service Award programs, clippings, correspondence, and other papers,1995 (Box 232, f. 17-19)
    - Scholarly Distinction Award (plaque), American Historical Association, 1997 (Box 248, f. 3)
    - Eminent Scholar Award (plaque), Academy of International Business, 2000 (Box 248, f. 4)
    - Doctor of Laws (Honorary), University of Delaware, 19 April 2002, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 7)
    - Doctor of Laws (Honorary), University of Delaware programs, correspondence and papers, 2002 (Box 233, f. 1)
    - Doctor of Business Administration (Honorary), Northeastern University, 15 June 2002 (Box 249, f. 6)
    - Doctor of Business Administration (Honorary), Northeastern University programs, correspondence and papers, 2002 (Box 233, f. 2)
    - Honorary Degree, Gothenburg University (never received) correspondence, 2003 (Box 233, f. 3)
- Series X. Ephemera, 1980-1991
  This series contains various ephemera and memorabilia collected by and presented to Alfred Chandler. Materials include medals, pins, a Japanese print and engraving and a ceremonial wand. Most of the materials are undated.
  - Alfred D. Chandler letterhead, undated (Box 246, f. 1)
  - Unidentified Japanese engraving, undated, (oversized) (Box OS 2, f. 1)
  - Unidentified Japanese print, undated, (oversized) (Map case)
  - Medal commemorating the inauguration of Paul Edward Gray as President of MIT, 6 Sept. 1980 (Box 247, item 1)
  - Medal for the Campaign for Harvard Business School, "To Educate Leaders Who Make a Difference in the World," undated (Box 247, item 3)
  - Medal for the 75th Anniversary Research Colloquium, Graduate School of Business Administration, Harvard University, 1983-1984 (Box 247, item 4)
  - Unidentified Italian poster, 1986, (oversized) (Box OS 3, f. 1)
  - Unidentified Japanese Medal engraved with Chandlers name, undated (Box 247, item 5)
  - Small plaque from Ohio State, "In appreciation from the College of Humanities," undated (Box 247, item 6)
  - Charles Babbage Institute paperweight, undated (Box 247, item 7)
  - John Harvard Society pins (2), undated (Box 247, item 8)
  - Newcomen Society pin, undated (Box 247, item 9)
  - Unidentified pin, undated (Box 247, item 10)
  - Metal cup from the MIT Corporation Visiting Committee for Humanities to Alfred D. Chandler, undated (Box 247, item 12)
  - Disc from the Association for the Management of Organization Design, 5 Sept. 1991 (Box 247, item 13)
  - Unidentified ceremonial wand, undated, (oversized) (Box OS 2)
  - Unidentified ceremonial gown, undated, (oversized) (Box OS 4)
- Series XI. Offprints, 1949-2005
  This series contains offprints of publications written by Alfred Chandler from 1949-2005. These offprints were kept on file by Alfred Chandler, most likely to distribute to researchers as requested.
  - Japan and the Theories of the Firm, [pub. undated] (Box 243, f. 1)
  - Comment on paper by Professor Conrad, [pub. undated] (Box 243, f. 2)
  - Managerial Enterprise and the Entrepreneurial Function, [pub. undated] (Box 243, f. 3)
  - Business and Government in an Increasingly Global Economy, [pub. undated] (Box 243, f. 4)
  - "Dupont, Dahlgren and the Civil War Nitre Shortage," Military Affairs, [pub. Fall 1949] (Box 243, f. 5)
  - "Henry Varnum Poor: Business Analyst, 1849-1887," Explorations in Entrepreneurial History, [pub. 1950] (Box 243, f. 6)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt and the Panama Canal: A Study in Administration," Explorations in Entrepreneurial History, [pub. 1951] (Box 243, f. 7)
  - Patterns of American Railroad Finance, 1830-1950, [pub. Fall 1954] (Box 243, f. 8)
  - Comments on Papers of Charles E. Perkins and Erastus Corning, [pub. 1956] (Box 243, f. 9)
  - Management Decentralization: An Historical Analysis, The Business History Review, [pub. June 1956] (Box 243, f. 10)
  - The Beginnings of "Big Business" in American Industry, [pub. 1959] (Box 243, f. 11)
  - Development, Diversification, and Decentralization, [pub. 1960] (Box 243, f. 12)
  - "Recent Developments in American Business Administration and their Conceptualization," Business History Review, [pub. Spring 1961] (Box 243, f. 13)
  - "Le Role De La Firme Dans L'Economie Americaine," Economie Appliquee, [pub. 1962] (Box 243, f. 14)
  - "Entrepreneurial Opportunity in Nineteenth Century America," Explorations in Entrepreneurial History, [pub. Fall 1963] (Box 243, f. 15)
  - "The Railroads: Pioneers in Modern Corporate Management," The Business History Review, [pub. Spring 1965] (Box 244, f. 1)
  - "The Role of Business in the US: A Historical Survey," Daedalus, 1968 (Box 244, f. 2)
  - "The Structure of American Industry in the Twentieth Century: A Historical Overview," The Business History Review, [pub. Fall 1969] (Box 244, f. 3)
  - "The Development of Large-Scale Economic Organizations in Modern America," Economic History, [pub. March 1970] (Box 244, f. 4)
  - "The Large Industrial Corporation and the Making of the Modern American Economy," Journal of Economic History, [pub. March 1971] (Box 244, f. 5)
  - "Chandler becomes Straus Professor," Harvard Business School Bulletin, [pub.1971] (Box 244, f. 6)
  - "Anthracite Coal and the Beginning of the Industrial Revolution in the United States, The Business History Review, [pub. Summer 1972] (Box 244, f. 7)
  - "Decision Making and Modern Institutional Change, The Journal of Economic History, [pub. 1973] (Box 244, f. 8)
  - "The Rise of Managerial Capitalism and its Impact on Investment Strategy in the Western World and Japan" (introduction), [pub. 1974] (Box 244, f. 9)
  - "Institutional Integration: An Approach to Comparative Studies of the History of Large-Scale Business Enterprise," Revue Economique, March 1976 (Box 244, f. 10)
  - Book review of America by Design: Science, Technology, and the Rise of Corporate Capitalism, by David F. Noble, [pub. 1977] (Box 244, f. 11)
  - "Fritz Redlich: Scholar and Friend," Journal of Economic History, [pub.1979] (Box 244, f. 12)
  - Law and the Formation of the Big Enterprises in the 19th and Early 20th Centuries, [pub. 1979] (Box 244, f. 13)
  - "Business and Public Policy," Harvard Business Review, [pub. 1979] (Box 244, f. 14)
  - "Managerial Capitalism: Have Modern Managers Replaced Market Forces in the Western Nations? The Journal of Corporate Governance, [pub. 1980] (Box 244, f. 15)
  - "Industrial Revolutions and Institutional Arrangements," The American Academy of Arts and Sciences, [pub. 1980] (Box 244, f. 16)
  - "The Growth of the Transnational Industrial Firm in the United States and the United Kingdom: A Comparative Analysis," The Economic History Review, [pub. 1980] (Box 244, f. 17)
  - Business and Public Policy, [pub. 1980] (Box 244, f. 18)
  - The American System and Modern Management, [pub. 1981] (Box 244, f. 19)
  - "Business History: What Is It About?" Journal of Contemporary Business, [pub. 1981] (Box 245, f. 1)
  - "Government v.s Business: An American Phenomenon, Enterprise: The Journal of Executive Action, [pub. 1982] (Box 245, f. 2)
  - "The M-Form: Industrial Groups, American Style," European Economic Review, [pub. 1982] (Box 245, f. 3)
  - The Place of the Modern Industrial Enterprise in Three Economies, [pub. 1983] (Box 245, f. 4)
  - "The Emergence of Managerial Capitalism," Business History Review, [pub. 1984] (Box 245, f. 5)
  - The Beginnings of Modern Industrial Corporations, [pub. 1986] (Box 245, f. 6)
  - Technological and Organizational Underpinnings of Modern Industrial Multinational Enterprise: The Dynamics of Competitive Advantage, [pub. 1986] (Box 245, f. 7)
  - Why History Matters to Managers, [pub. 1986] (Box 245, f. 8)
  - "A Framework for Analyzing the Modern Multinational Enterprise and its Competitive Advantage," Business and Economic History, [pub. 1987] (Box 245, f. 9)
  - The Historian and the Enterprise, [pub. 1988] (Box 245, f. 10)
  - Book review of The Ultimate Entrepreneur: The Story of Ken Olsen, [pub. 1989] (Box 245, f. 11)
  - "Advice to Small Companies: Think Big (interview), Forbes, [pub. 1989] (Box 245, f. 12)
  - Scale and Scope, Appendix Tables, [pub. 1990] (Box 245, f. 13-14)
  - "Scale and Scope: A Review Colloquium," Business History Review, [pub. Winter 1990] (Box 245, f. 15-16)
  - "Response to the Contributors to the Review Colloquium on Scale and Scope," Business History Review, [pub. Winter 1990] (Box 250, f. 1-2)
  - "The Enduring Logic of Industrial Success," Harvard Business Review, [pub. March-April 1990] (Box 250, f. 3)
  - Alfred Chandler and the Dynamics of Business History, Harvard Business School Bulletin, [pub. Apr. 1990] (Box 250, f. 4-5)
  - Favorites of Fortune: Technology Growth, and Economic Development since the Industrial Revolution, [pub. 1991] (Box 250, f. 6)
  - "The Functions of the HQ Unit in the Multibusiness Firm," Strategic Management Journal, [pub. 1991] (Box 250, f. 7)
  - Learning and Technological Change: The Perspective from Business History, [pub. 1991] (Box 250, f. 8)
  - Zaibatsu, [pub. 1992] (Box 250, f. 9)
  - "What is a Firm?"European Economic Review, [pub.1992] (Box 250, f. 10)
  - "Corporate Strategy, Structure and Control Methods in the United States During the 20th Century," Industrial and Corporate Change, [pub. 1992] (Box 250, f. 11)
  - "History and Management Practice and Thought, Management Laureates: A Collection of Autobiographical Essays, [pub. 1992] (Box 250, f. 12-13)
  - "Organizational Capability and Competitive Advantage," Business History, [pub. Jan. 1992] (Box 250, f. 14)
  - "Organizational Capabilities and the Economic History of the Industrial Enterprise," Journal of Economic Perspectives, [pub. Summer 1992] (Box 250, f. 15-16)
  - "Organizational Capabilities and Industrial Restructuring: A Historical Analysis," Journal of Comparative Economics, [pub. 1993] (Box 251, f. 1)
  - Processes of Production in Twentieth Century United States, [pub. 1993] (Box 251, f. 2)
  - "Debates and Controversies in Economic History," Proceedings from the Eleventh International Economic History Congress, Milan, [pub. Sept. 1994] (Box 251, f. 3-4)
  - "A Historical Perspective on U.S. Industrial Leadership, Business and Economic History, [pub. Winter 1995] (Box 251, f. 5-6)
  - "Hughesian History of Technology and Chandlerian Business History: Parallels, Departures and Critics," History and Technology, [pub. 1995] (Box 251, f. 7)
  - International Economy and Large Industrial Enterprises in the Twentieth Century, [pub. Sept.1996] (Box 251, f. 8)
  - "The Computer Industry: The First Half-Century, "Competing in the Age of Digital Convergency, [pub. 1997] (Box 251, f. 9-10)
  - Response to the Symposium: Framing Business History, [pub. 2005] (Box 251, f. 11)